A Guide to the William J. Ronan papers FA1299
Rockefeller Archive Center
William J. Ronan papers
1945-1988
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ronan, William J. (William John) (1912-)
FA1299
9.24 Cubic Feet 23 boxes - 9 legal document containers, 9 letter document containers, 1 half-letter document container, 1 half-legal document container, 1 oversize document container, and 1 clamshell document container
Biographical / Historical
William J. Ronan was born on Nov. 8, 1912. He graduated from Syracuse University in 1934 and began teaching government at New York University in 1938. Ronan earned a PhD in international law and diplomacy from NYU in 1940, where he was hired as an assistant professor of government. From 1953-1958, he served as the Dean of NYU's Robert F. Wagner Graduate School of Public Service. Ronan was appointed Secretary to the Governor in Nelson Rockefeller's administration and served in this capacity from 1959-1966. He left this position to work for the newly-created Metropolitan Commuter Transportation Authority which became the Metropolitan Transportation Authority in 1968. Ronan served as the first chairman of the MTA until 1974. Under his leadership, the MTA began major improvement projects. He left the MTA to serve as chairman of the Port Authority of New York and New Jersey until 1977. From 1980-1986, Ronan served as the Director of the National Health Council. He remained an advisor to the Rockefeller family until 1990 and retired from public service to work as an adviser to transportation companies, government agencies, and nonprofits as well as serve on corporate boards. Ronan died in 2014 at the age of 101.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
This material was donated and transferred to the RAC in 2016 by Diana Ronan Quasha and ingested by RAC as Accession 2016:040
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC. Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. To request an access surrogate be made, or if you are unsure if there is an access surrogate, please contact an archivist.
When requesting to view audiovisual material, please refer to the Title and the AV Number (example: AV 1916). Researchers are asked to check the "Restrictions" note for each Title. If a Title does not currently have an access copy, please contact a RAC archivist for further instruction.
Scope and Contents
The William J. Ronan papers consist of materials related to Ronan's years of service as Secretary to the Governor of the State of New York during Nelson Rockefeller's administration, Chairman of the Metropolitan Transportation Authority, and Chairman of the Port Authority of New York and New Jersey. The collection contains diaries and planners documenting his daily activities as well as clippings, reports, photographs, awards, and a personal memoir.
Related Materials
Nelson A. Rockefeller gubernatorial records, William J. Ronan, Series 29 (FA371)
Arrangement
The William J. Ronan papers are arranged into one series: Personal Papers
Rockefeller, Nelson A. (Nelson Aldrich), 1908-1979 -- Political and social views; Transportation -- New York Metropolitan Area; New York (State) -- Politics and government; Presidential campaigns -- United States
- Personal Papers, 1945-1988; 1; 9.24 Cubic Feet 23 containers
  - Standard Diary, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - National Diary for 1967 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Green's Diary, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - National Diary for 1963 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - National Diary for 1966 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Green's Diary, 1962 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - National Diary for 1966 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Daily Reminder, 1979 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Green's Diary, 1965 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Diary, 1973 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Diary, 1974 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - The Standard Diary, 1961 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - The Standard Diary, 1960 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - The Standard Diary, 1959 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - State of New York: Temporary State Commission on Coordination of State Activities: Staff Report on Public Authorities Under New York State (2 copies), 1956 March 21 (Box 7, Folder 15-16)
  - Metropolitan Transportation Authority (MTA) Annual Report, 1968-1972 (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - Metropolitan Transportation Authority (MTA) Annual Report, 1968-1972 (Box 8, Folder 18)
  - Continental Diary, 1969 (Box 8, Folder 19)
  - Continental Diary, 1968 (Box 8, Folder 20)
  - National Time Line, 1977 (Box 9, Folder 21)
  - Standard Diary, 1972 (Box 9, Folder 22)
  - The New York Red Book, 1959 (Box 9, Folder 23)
  - Standard Diary, 1977 (Box 10, Folder 24)
  - Nomination of Nelson A. Rockefeller to be Vice President of the United States, Senate and House Hearings and Reports, 1974 (Box 11, Folder 25)
    Scope and Contents
    Bound volume
  - Manual for the Use of the Legislature of the State of New York, 1955 (Box 11, Folder 26)
  - Manual for the Use of the Legislature of the State of New York, 1959 (Box 11, Folder 27)
  - The New York Red Book, 1962-1963 (Box 12, Folder 28)
  - Manual for the Use of the Legislature of the State of New York (2 copies), 1961-1962 (Box 12, Folder 29-30)
  - Manual for the Use of the Legislature of the State of New York, 1966-1967 (Box 12, Folder 31)
  - New York City Transit Authority GSI Presentation Slides, 1972 March 1; 2016:040:001 (Box 19, Folder 83)
  - Port Authority Bus Terminal photograph, undated; 2016:040:002 (Box 19, Folder 84)
    Board of Commissioners (?) group photo
  - The Strategy and Art of Political Campaigning, Second Carbon Copy, 1967-1968 (Box 13, Folder 32)
  - Evolution of the Public Transportation Industry, undated (Box 13, Folder 33)
  - William J. Ronan - Personal, 1946-1987 (Box 13, Folder 34)
    Reports, clippings, and correspondence - Monitor: The Voice of Industry in New York State May 1960, Program for 31st Annual Dean's Day at New York University, Certificate of Satisfactory Service in the Navy 1946, Clippings from 1987, Nassau County Commerce and Industry News 1982, and correspondence
  - Hon. William J. Ronan Commissioner, Port Authority of New York and New Jersey portrait, undated; 2016:040:003 (Box 19, Folder 85)
  - Lord and Lady Snow with Dr. Ronan photograph, undated; 2016:040:004 (Box 19, Folder 86)
    Note on back: Ronan, Tissol (sp?), Byrne Tokyo 1970?
  - American Public Transit Association - Hall of Fame Plaque Presentation photograph, 1985; 2016:040:005 (Box 19, Folder 87)
  - World Trade Center photographs, 1975 December 15; 2016:040:006 (Box 19, Folder 88)
    Opening Day Ceremony of the Observation Deck Atop the World Trade Center, Port Authority Chairman William J. Ronan speaking
  - Urban Mass Transportation Administration - Presented to Dr. William J. Ronan in Commemoration of the Start of the Smokeless Cable Development Program, 1976 March 17; 2016:040:007 (Box 21, Folder 106)
  - American Public Transit Association Hall of Fame 1985 Plaque, 2016:040:008 (Box 22, Folder 108)
  - Untitled Group Photograph, undated; 2016:040:009 (Box 19, Folder 89)
  - American Transit Association 93rd Annual Meeting Program, New York, 1974 October 13-17 (Box 13, Folder 35)
  - Special Court Regional Rail Reorganization Act of 1973 - Testimony of Dr. William J Ronan, 1980 October 15 (Box 13, Folder 36)
    Concerning likely actions of public agencies and authorities with respect to the Northeast Corridor properties in the absence of the Regional Rail Reorganization Act of 1973 submitted on behalf of the Penn Central Corporation and certain affiliated Penn Central Transferors
  - Mass Transit 6, Volume 5 - Ronan still making Headlines by Frank Mazza, 1978 June (Box 13, Folder 37)
  - Mass Transit 8, Volume 2 - Message from Ronan: Get Back to Reality by Frank Mazza (2 copies), 1975 September (Box 13, Folder 38)
  - Review and Evaluation of Port Authority of New York and New Jersey (PA) Actions Relative to Expense Account Irregularities Audit Report NY-Auth-12-79, 1978 June 26 (Box 13, Folder 39)
  - Revised Draft of Senate Bill 386 - Joint Conference Committee, Institute for Rapid Transit (IRT), 1974 October (Box 13, Folder 40)
  - Institute for Rapid Transit (IRT) Newsletter, 1970 August (Box 13, Folder 41)
  - The New York Times Section 11 Advertisement - Millions on the Move, 1971 June 20; 2016:040:010 (Box 21, Folder 105)
  - Dedication Ceremony, General Electric Commuter Car, New Haven, 1971 November 12; 2016:040:012 (Box 19, Folder 90)
  - National Diary for 1970 (Box 13, Folder 42)
  - Page Describing Nelson Rockefeller's Funeral, undated (Box 13, Folder 43)
  - National Time Line 1975 (Box 14, Folder 44)
  - National Time Line 1974 (Box 14, Folder 45)
  - National Time Line 1974 - Removed Clippings, 1971-1975 (Box 14, Folder 45a)
  - Business Cards, William J. Ronan, Secretary to the Governor, State of New York, undated (Box 14, Folder 46)
  - Fabric with "2" stitched on, undated (Box 14, Folder 47)
  - Standard Diary, 1975 (Box 15, Folder 48)
  - Untitled group photographs, 1959; 2016:040:013 (Box 19, Folder 91)
    Water conference?
  - Personal Memoir, undated (Box 15, Folder 49-53)
    Folder 49.) Includes chapters dedicated to the Port Authority of New York and New Jersey, Folder 50.) Only in New York, Odd Jobs, Entering Academia: Instructor in Government, Marriage and Honeymoon, Navy Days, Return to NYU and Career in Academia, Home Sweet Homes Long Island, People and Personalities, Folder 51.) World Trade Center Saga, Second Campaign 1962, Folder 52.) The Rockefeller Years, First Campaign 1958, Secretary to the Governor, Folder 53.) A Classic Campaign 1966, Albany Renaissance, The Quest for Presidential Nomination
  - Personal Memoir, undated (Box 16, Folder 54-57)
    Folder 54.) Tri-State Transportation and Planning Commission, Creating and Operating the Metropolitan Transportation Authority, Folder 55.) Buying and Modernizing the Long Island Railroad, Securing Two Vital Regional Airports, The Port Authority of New York and New Jersey, Folder 56.) Tracking Transportation: The New York Metropolitan Transportation Authority, Tri-State Transportation and Planning Commission, Creating and Operating the Metropolitan Transportation Authority, Folder 57.) Buying and Modernizing the Long Island Railroad, The New York City Transit Authority Subway Rescue and Modernization, Securing Two Vital Regional Airports
  - Metropolitan Transit Authority (MTA) Chairman Complimentary Metropolitan Suburban Bus Authority (MSBA) Rail Pass and Business Cards, 1974 (Box 16, Folder 58)
  - Photographs and Programs, 1975; 2016:040:014 (Box 20, Folder 94)
    Dowling College Honorary Degree Presentation, Unidentified photos of events, meetings, and ribbon cuttings, Salute to the Vice President of the United States Program 1975, Invitation and Menu for the Vice President's Home Housewarming Party 1975, Group Photo NYU School of Public and Business Administration
  - Queen Elizabeth Visit Photographs, 1976 July 9; 2016:040:014 (Box 20, Folder 95)
  - Visit to the World Trade Center of Their Majesties the King and Queen of Spain photographs, 1976 June 4; 2016:040:014 (Box 20, Folder 96)
  - Photographs of Navy Service Members, Nelson Rockefeller, and Ships, Bicentennial Celebration (?), 1976 July 4; 2017:040:014 (Box 20, Folder 97)
  - Photographs, undated; 2017:040:014 (Box 20, Folder 98)
    Photographs of various events, including the opening day ceremony of the observation deck atop the World Trade Center, photographs with rail cars, ribbon-cuttings, and meetings with world leaders
  - Photographs, undated; 2017:040:014 (Box 20, Folder 99)
    Unknown aerial photo, press briefing, group photo
  - Photograph signed by Nelson Rockefeller, undated; 2016:040:021 (Box 21)
    Separated Materials
    Special format items have been separated from the above listed file and assigned a unique separation number, as noted. Requests to access open special formats should reference the unique separation number.
  - Aviation Education Day Photograph, 1967 September 30; 2016:040:014a (Box 21, Folder 100)
  - Photographs, 1969; 2016:040:014b (Box 21, Folder 101)
    Unknown William J. Ronan swearing-in ceremony and Signing of Contract for Construction of 63rd St. East River Tunnel, October 24, 1969
  - Unidentified Photograph, undated; 2016:040:014c (Box 21, Folder 102)
  - First Riders' Club Certificates - BC Transit (British Columbia), undated; 2016:040:011, 2016:040:015 (Box 21, Folder 104)
    Presented to Bill and Elena Ronan
  - The National Health Council Testimonial of Achievement, 1986 April 1; 2016:040:016 (Box 21, Folder 103)
  - Who's Who in the World 25th Edition, William J. Ronan Profile, 2008 (Box 16, Folder 59)
  - Correspondence with New York University and the Department of State, 1946-1958 (Box 16, Folder 60)
  - Clippings (3 folders), 1956-1974 (Box 16, Folder 61-63)
  - The Nelson Rockefeller Collection (2 copies), 1979-1980 (Box 16, Folder 64)
    Art catalog created by William J. Ronan
  - Clippings, 1974 (Box 16, Folder 65)
  - Clippings, 1945-1985 (Box 21, Folder 107)
    Also contains assorted pamphlets and programs from events
  - Reports, Ephemera, and Clippings, 1960-1977 (Box 16, Folder 66)
    Dowling College Commencement 1974 Program, Downtown-Lower Manhattan Association, Inc. Twelfth Annual Dinner 1962, Program and Seating List for Dinner in Honor of King Juan Carlos I and Queen Sofia of Spain, National Bureau of Economic Research, Inc. Executive Summary 1977, The Institute for Socioeconomic Studies Annual Dinner Conference on Welfare Reform 1975, Certificate for Ronan's Membership in the National Academy of Public Administration 1968, 1968-1973 The Ten-Year Program at the Halfway Mark - MTA, and related clippings and correspondence
  - Photographs, 1976-1986; 2016:040:017 (Box 19, Folder 92)
    Presentation of Emerald Society Inc. New York City Transit plaque honoring William J. Ronan, Chairman's Club Nassau County group photo Spring 1986, "Take Stock in America/'76" New York City Savings Bonds Committee Luncheon in Honor of William E. Simon, Secretary of the Treasury 1976, photos from unidentified events, and World Trade Centers Association 7th General Assembly Peace and Prosperity through World Trade - Korea 1976
  - Photographs, 1981 (Box 19, Folder 93)
    1981 Gold Medal Award Ceremony, the majority are undated and unidentified photographs from various meetings and events
  - Pocket Planners, 1963-1988 (Box 17, Folder 67-76, Box 18, Folder 77-79)
    Individual pocket planners for individual years: 1967, 1984, 1964, 1965, 1982, 1973, 1968, 1981, 1985 (Republican Senatorial Inner Circle), 1987, 1963, 1988, 1978
  - Address Books, undated (Box 18, Folder 80-82)
  - Vice President Nelson A. Rockefeller Address Delivered in the Senate Chambers, 1974 December 19; 2016:040:018 (Box 21, Folder 109)
  - Metropolitan Transportation Authority Certificate of Honorary Membership, undated; 2016:040:019 (Box 21, Folder 110)
  - Commemorative Pen and Letter Framed, undated; 2016:040:020 (Item 2015:040:020)
  - White House Meeting on Transportation for New Yorkers, 1972 July 7 (Box 20, Folder 111)
  - Villa La Pointe du Cap, Circa 1990s; VHS; Sound, Color, 25 minutes (Box 22, Tape AV 12118)
    Conditions Governing Access
    Access copy available.
  - A Tribute to Nelson A. Rockefeller on the Occasion of the 40th Anniversary of his First Gubernatorial Campaign, 1998; VHS; Sound, Black and white, Color, 13 minutes (Box 22, Tape AV 12119)
  - Bill's Surprise 90th Birthday, 2002 November 19; Sound, Color, 53 minutes; VHS (Box 22, Tape AV 12120)
  - William Ronan's Home Movies, 1948; VHS; Silent, Color, 12 minutes (Box 22, Tape AV 12121)